{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In self-defense, this man murdered a mutinous sailor named Blackton on the island of Tobago. Years after completing his most notable service, this man became a rear admiral in the Russian Imperial Navy under Catherine the Great. When encountering the Serapis, this man supposedly shouted, \"I have not yet begun to fight!\" For ten points, name this captain of the Bonhomme Richard [[bohn-ohm-ree-SHAHRD]] and Revolutionary War hero, sometimes called the \"Father of the American Navy.\"",
      "answer": [
        "John Paul Jones",
        "John Paul"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A conflict in this region began in the Battle of the Bogside in 1969. The Sunningdale power-sharing agreement broke down after a general strike in this region, and a sectarian conflict in this region led to the fall of its parliament at Stormont. Protesters in this territory’s city of Derry were fired on by paratroopers in “Bloody Sunday.” For ten points, name this smallest constituent country of the United Kingdom in which the Troubles started in the late 1960s.",
      "answer": "Northern Ireland or Tuaisceart Éireann"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rebellions near Hanguguan led this dynasty's \"Gentleman of the Palace,\" Zhao Gao, to lead a coup to assassinate the emperor. Shang Yang's philosophy of Legalism was the primary ideology of this dynasty, which ended the Warring States period. The first emperor of this dynasty died from an \"Elixir of Immortality\" and was responsible for the terracotta army in Xi'an. For ten points, name this short-lived dynasty from which the western name for China is derived.",
      "answer": [
        "Qin ] Dynasty",
        "Chin Dynasty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A woman in drag named Tullia is nearly hanged by a leader of this empire, Ottone, in a Vivaldi pastoral opera. The Coronation of Poppaea, the last by Claudio Montiverdi, concerns the title mistress's attempt to be crowned queen of this empire. A daughter of a Chief Druid named Norma jumps in a fire with her lover Pollione, the pro-consul of Gaul in this empire, at the end of a Bellini opera. Cesare [[CHAY-zah-ray]] e Cleopatra is set in, for ten points, which ancient European empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Roman Empire",
        "Rome"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In an effort to promote this policy, the Technicolor film The Gang's All Here, starring Carmen Miranda, was partially subsidized by the federal government. The immediate effect of this policy ended the lengthy occupation of Haiti and terminated the Platt Amendment, which had established U.S. hegemony over Cuba. Non-interventionism in Latin America was promoted by, for ten points, which New Deal-era foreign policy?",
      "answer": [
        "Good Neighbor Policy",
        "Política de Buena Vecindad",
        "or Política de Boa Vizinhança"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Akbar the Great ordered a Persian language version of this work be produced known as the Razmnama [[rah-zem-NAH-mah]], which translates to \"Book of War.\" In this work, a lengthy journey of exile to the Himalayas leads to the death of Draupadi. The Pandava and Kaurava families clash in this work's Kurukshetra War, following a failed peace conference led by Krishna. For ten points, name this Hindu epic written in Sanskrit which contains the Bhagavad Gita.",
      "answer": "Mahabharata ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the Syr Darya, this empire's forces burned their entire baggage train during the \"Day of Thirst\" while being harassed by the Turgesh Khanate. Forces of this dynasty's Yazid I killed Husayn ibn Ali to win the Battle of Karbala, sparking the Second Fitna. This dynasty fled to Iberia after being overthrown by the Abbasid dynasty. For ten points, name this successor of the \"Rightly Guided\" caliphs, an empire which conquered much of North Africa and Western Asia.",
      "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's work on animal respiration utilized his friend and human guinea pig Armand Séguin [[seh-GWEEN]]. This scientist disproved the historically popular phlogiston [[FLOH-jis-tahn]] theory by showing that nothing new is produced by combustion. This man formulated the law of conservation of mass and named oxygen and hydrogen before being executed during the French Revolution. For ten points, name this French scientist who is considered the father of modern chemistry.",
      "answer": "Antoine Lavoisier"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because Septimius Severus was born in Leptis Magna, a former colony of this city, he gave all of its people Roman citizenship at the end of the 2nd Century. Alexander the Great crucified 2,000 survivors in this city after he built an artificial causeway to subjugate its island portion. This city names a type of purple dye from the murex snail, most commonly associated with imperial power in antiquity. For ten points, name this Phoenician metropolis in modern-day Lebanon.",
      "answer": [
        "Tyre",
        "Tyros",
        "or Sur 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The short-lived Free State of Bottleneck was created in this region from a narrow gap in the Wisper Valley between Allied occupation zones. A brief \"Cis\" Republic in this region was a client state of Revolutionary France before being annexed. A pact recognizing this region's western borders was the principal portion of the Locarno Treaties in 1925. In direct violation of the Treaty of Versailles [[vehr-SYE]], Adolf Hitler ordered the remilitarization of, for ten points, what region in 1936?",
      "answer": "Rhineland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man established a short-lived Government-in-exile known as the Sigmaringen Enclave. During one conflict, this man's defensive strategy prevented mass mutinies following the disastrous Nivelle Offensive against Imperial Germany. A cabinet led by this man formally surrendered to Nazi Germany during the Peace at Compiègne [[cohm-pee- EHN]] following a 1940 blitzkrieg. For ten points, name this Marshal of France who led the collaborationist Vichy Regime.",
        "answer": "Philippe Pétain ] or Henri Philippe Benoni Omer Pétain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both Prime Minister Clemenceau and Marshal Pétain disliked this other French general, who took Supreme Command of Allied Forces during the surprise German Spring Offensive of 1918 and later accepted the German cessation of hostilities.",
        "answer": "Ferdinand Foch"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the first of these wars, bureaucratic corruption led to wrong caliber shells being outfitted on Admiral Ding Ruchang's ships, resulting in his loss at the Battle of Yalu River. The Treaty of Shimonoseki ended the first of these wars, giving one power hegemony over Korea. The second of these wars began after the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred outside Beijing. For ten points, give this name of two wars between two East Asian superpowers, the first fought between the Qing and the Meiji governments.",
        "answer": "Sino-Japanese War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Shimonoseki gave Japan a \"most favored nation status\" in terms of trade with China. It was later dubbed one of these one-sided agreements the Qing signed with various Western powers.",
        "answer": "Unequal Treaties or Bùpíngděng Tiáoyuē"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After failing to provide the donativum to this organization, a rogue member of it slashed the throat of Pertinax. This organization auctioned off the title of imperator, eventually bestowing the title to Didius Julianus for 25,000 sesterces. Earlier that year, this elite unit's prefect paid off Narcissus to kill his wrestling partner, Emperor Commodus. For ten points, name this imperial bodyguard who often interfered in Roman politics.",
        "answer": [
          "Praetorian Guard",
          "Praetorian Cohort",
          "Cohortēs praetōriae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Praetorian Guard was dissolved after Constantine the Great defeated Maxentius at this battle, where Constantine supposedly painted a Chi Rho [[KYE ROH]] on the shields of his soldiers.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Milvian Bridge",
          "Battle of Ponte Milvio 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2015, in the area surrounding this waterway, an Economic Zone was established with custom rates set at zero as part of a larger \"Area Development Project.\" Operation Musketeer was a planned invasion of this structure by Britain and France, which occurred during a \"Crisis\" around this structure's nationalization by Gamel Abdel Nasser. For ten points, name this waterway that connects the Mediterranean Sea and the Red Sea.",
        "answer": "Suez Canal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Israelis commonly refer to the Suez Crisis as a war for this continent-connecting peninsula located in eastern Egypt.",
        "answer": "Sinai Peninsula or Sīna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Pliant Mahon [[PLY-ant muh-HAHN]] received a fourteen-year prison sentence during this conflict in which Deputy Bill Dempsey was killed by Frank Phillips. This conflict escalated over the failure of Perry Cline to win a lawsuit regarding a deed of land. Jim Vance may have started this conflict, in which one side’s cabin was burned during the New Year’s Massacre. Figures like Randolph \"Ole Ran'l\" and \"Devil Anse\" took part in, for ten points, what feud between two rural families in West Virginia and Kentucky?",
        "answer": "Hatfield-McCoy Feud"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both families were involved in the illicit trade of which specific type of bootleg liquor common in the South whose name is derived from it being made at night?",
        "answer": "Moonshine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Taney [[TAW-nee]]-era case Strader v. Graham held that this law's prohibition of slavery did not extend to states created from the territory it covered. Little Turtle's War was fought in the territory created by this act, which mandated appointments for governors and population thresholds for future statehood. For ten points, name this organic act that established a namesake territory between the Mississippi and Ohio rivers.",
        "answer": "Northwest Ordinance"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Northwest Territory is considered the first example of this kind of land in U.S. history, which has yet to be dedicated to a specific use. The Homestead Act allowed applicants to settle this kind of land and convert it to private property.",
        "answer": "Public Domain"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's 1960 independence was established by the London and Zürich Agreements. One leader of this country survived four assassination attempts and was given the title \"Ethnarch.\" This country, whose first president was Makarios III [[mah-KAHR- yohss the THIRD]], pursued a union with a larger country in a process called Enosis [[ee- NOH-siss]]. This country's north has been occupied since 1973 by Turkey and is divided by the Green Line. For ten points, name this island nation, controlled successively by the Ottomans and Great Britain, in the eastern Mediterranean.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Cyprus or Kypriaki Dimokratia",
          "or Kibris Cumhuriyeti",
          "Kypros"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "It has been suggested that the word \"Cyprus\" derives from the Sumerian word for this metal, which was found in abundance on the island.",
        "answer": "Copper or Cu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During World War Two, this composer served his local community as a fireman, and although he was denounced several times by Josef Stalin, this composer joined the Communist Party of the Soviet Union in 1960. This composer had to premiere one piece in Kuybyshev [[KOY-bish-shev]] after being evacuated due to a Nazi siege of a Russian city. For ten points, name this Soviet composer of the \"Leningrad Symphony.\"",
        "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich or Dmitri Dmitriyevich Shostakovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shostakovich was greatly influenced by this Russian composer who was known for a piece which caused civil unrest after its 1913 debut, The Rite of Spring.",
        "answer": "Igor Stravinsky or Igor Fyodorovich Stravinsky"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Connecticut History",
      "prompt": "Concerning Connecticut, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city which names a failed treaty with the Dutch.",
          "answer": "Hartford"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president born there who was in office during Operation Iraqi Freedom.",
          "answer": [
            "George Walker Bush",
            "Bush 43",
            "Bush the Younger"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern state in which Connecticut had its \"Western Reserve.\"",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Senator and signer of the Constitution who proposed the Connecticut Compromise.",
          "answer": "Roger Sherman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slave ship towed into its waters after a revolt led by Joseph Cinqué [[sin-KEH]].",
          "answer": "La Amistad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic senator, later an independent, whom Al Gore chose as his running mate in 2000.",
          "answer": "Joe Lieberman or Joseph Isadore Lieberman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor elected in 1975, the first woman in the U.S. elected in her own right.",
          "answer": [
            "Ella T. Grasso or Ella Rosa Giovianna Oliva Grasso",
            "Ella Tambussi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Baptist association which received a Thomas Jefferson letter mentioning \"separation between Church and State.\"",
          "answer": "Danbury Baptist Association or Danbury Baptists 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hungary",
      "prompt": "Concerning Hungary, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital which takes its name from the combination of two Medieval cities.",
          "answer": "Budapest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor once led by the Habsburgs, which formed a dual monarchy in 1867.",
          "answer": [
            "Austria",
            "Osterreich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of the Conservative Fidesz [[FEE-dess]] Party, who became prime minister in 2010.",
          "answer": "Viktor Orbán or Viktor Mihály Orbán"
        },
        {
          "question": "Olympic aquatic sport whose 1956 semifinals match turned bloody due to tensions with the USSR.",
          "answer": "Water polo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saint who was crowned first King of Hungary in the year 1000.",
          "answer": [
            "Stephen I",
            "Szent István király",
            "or Štefan Veľký"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral and reluctant Nazi collaborator who was overthrown and replaced by the Fascist Arrow Cross Party.",
          "answer": [
            "Miklós Horthy ] or Nicholas Horthy",
            "or Miklós Horthy de Nagybánya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of Hungary who settled the Magyar [[MAH-gyar]] tribes in the Carpathian Basin.",
          "answer": "Árpád"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mixed form of communism practiced in Hungary by János Kádár [[YAH-nohsh KAH- dahr]].",
          "answer": "\"Goulash Communism\""
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Kamakura Period",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Kamakura Period of Japan, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Japanese warrior nobles which first appeared during the period.",
          "answer": "Samurai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military position first held by Minamoto no Yoritomo [[mih-nah-MOH-toh noh toh- ree-TOH-moh]], making him the de facto head of Japan.",
          "answer": "Shogun"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Divine Wind,\" likely a typhoon, which sunk the Mongol navy in their attempt to conquer Japan.",
          "answer": "Kamikaze ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sect of Buddhism introduced to Japan by Dōgen [[DOH-gen]].",
          "answer": "Zen Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Landless warriors whom warlords hired to supplement armies during the dynastic conflicts of the period.",
          "answer": "Rōnin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clan whose leader Takauji [[tah-kah-OO-jee]] established himself as leader of Japan in 1337.",
          "answer": [
            "Ashikaga ]",
            "Ashikaga shogunate"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Brief \"Restoration\" by Go-Daigo [[goh-\"die\"-GOH]] which overthrew the Kamakura in favor of direct imperial rule.",
          "answer": "Kenmu Restoration or Kenmu no shinsei"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Taira [[tah-EE-rah]] and Minamoto clans that led to the establishment of the Kamakura.",
          "answer": [
            "Genpei War ]",
            "Genpei kassen",
            "Jisho-Juei War 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker debated fellow pragmatist John Dewey after publishing Democracy and Social Ethics. This thinker espoused pacifism in books such as Newer Ideals of Peace. This first U.S. woman to win the Nobel (20 pts)",
        "Peace Prize drew on the ideas of England's Toynbee Hall when expanding the use of \"friendly visitors\" at an institution she co-founded with Ellen Gates Starr in (10 pts)",
        "Chicago. For ten points, name this pioneering social worker who founded Hull House."
      ],
      "answer": "Jane Addams or Laura Jane Addams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Near the end of his life, this man prepared the defense of Gibraltar after it was threatened by the Castilian king Alfonso XI [[the eleventh]]. This Berber's sixteen month hajj to Mecca continued as he joined a caravan aiming to trade within the Il- khanate. The (*) travelogue known informally as The Rihla recounts this man's visit to Yuan China, the Swahili Coast, and the Indian subcontinent. (*) For ten points, name this medieval Moroccan explorer who traveled over ten times as far as Marco Polo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ibn Battuta",
        "Abu Abdullah Muhammad ibn Battuta"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man delivered a speech condemning Operation Danube, declaring it was a \"grave error and constituted a serious danger to peace in Europe.\" One of this man's first actions as head of state was to pass Decree 770 in order to boost (20 pts)",
        "population by making abortion illegal. Following this man's overthrow, he and his wife were found guilty of corruption and (10 pts)",
        "genocide and were sentenced to death by the National Salvation Front. For ten points, name this Romanian communist dictator."
      ],
      "answer": "Nicolae Ceaușescu ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Young Turk Enver Pasha ordered this city's \"September Days,\" a series of anti- Armenian pogroms committed by the \"Army of Islam.\" A part of the larger \"Case Blue,\" Operation Edelweiss [[AY-del-vice]] (20 pts)",
        "was a Wehrmacht [[VARE-mahkt]] advance meant to cripple the Soviet petroleum supply by capturing this city's (10 pts)",
        "oilfields. For ten points, which Caspian port city was made capital of independent Azerbaijan following the dissolution of the USSR?"
      ],
      "answer": "Baku or Baki"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician and one-time New York governor names a Cornell Law School building. When David Brewer died, William Howard Taft nominated this man to replace him in his highest office. This man resigned from the Supreme Court in 1916 to unsuccessfully (20 pts)",
        "run for president against Woodrow Wilson, and in 1921, this man became Warren Harding's (10 pts)",
        "Secretary of State. For ten points, name this man who returned to the court to serve as Chief Justice from 1930 to 1941."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes, Sr. 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A “Great” revolt against colonial rule in this country in the 1920s was led by Sultan Pasha al-Atrash [[ah-TRAHSH]]. Michel Aflaq [[ah-FLAHK]] created the first (20 pts)",
        "Ba’ath [[bah-AHTH] party in this country. United with another Arab country in the United Arab Republic, this country lost the Golan [[GOH-lahn]] (10 pts)",
        "Heights to Israel in the Yom Kippur War. For ten points, name this country, united with Lebanon in a French mandate and now ruled by the Assad [[ah-SAHD]] family."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Syrian Arab Republic or Al Jumhuriyah al Arabiyah as Suriyah",
        "Arab Kingdom of Syria",
        "State of Syria"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Galen's [[GAY-lens]] work On Fallacies, he criticized this philosophical school's inability to use clear language and their disbelief in the duality of the soul. The emperor Domitian [[doh-MIH-shun]] banished one of this school's philosophers, Epictetus [[eh-PIK-teh-tus]], (20 pts)",
        "who returned to Greece and taught Arrian. \"Virtue is the only good\" was often espoused by supporters of this philosophical school. Zeno (10 pts)",
        "of Citium founded, for ten points, what school of philosophy which includes the writer of Meditations, Emperor Marcus Aurelius?"
      ],
      "answer": "Stoicism or Stoics"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was subpoenaed for his knowledge of Operation Red Dog, a neo-Nazi attempt to seize the island of Dominica in the early 1980s. This man is the oldest person to receive an electoral vote, which he received from Bill Greene in the 2016 election. This first chairman of the (20 pts)",
        "Citizens for a Sound Economy organized the early Tea Party protests in the 2000s. The (10 pts)",
        "father of Kentucky senator Rand is, for ten points, which Libertarian presidential candidate, a former representative from Texas?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ron Paul or Ron Ernest Paul"
    }
  ]
}